Chapter 6
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek, Venlil Space Corps,
Venlil-Human Exchange Program

Date [standardized human time]:
August 21, 2136

The first humans to appear on a Venlil broadcast were concealed by a vac suit, and did not speak a word. The watching world had just crawled from our bunkers, only to find our leaders linking arms with predators. The immediate closure of the borders was the sole thing that prevented a mass exodus, and word from getting back to the Federation. There was a great deal of skepticism from the public, as Governor Tarva proclaimed that these beasts were peaceful. We were all waiting for them to throw their lot in with the Arxur and prove her wrong.

Instead, the United Nations pledged military aid days later, and showered Venlil Prime with food donations. Our citizens slowly warmed to the primates, touched by their outpouring of generosity. The sum of their good works quieted the voices calling for human extinction, for the most part. The Terran astronauts were relentless too, on a television tour espousing peace. Their behavior reflected well on their species as a whole.

But at the end of the day, few wanted to meet a predator in the flesh. As human volunteers took to the stars, the scientific communities of two worlds worked to smooth over our first interactions. We found ourselves inundated by Terran entertainment, granting us a peek behind their bestial exterior. The first literature Earth shared with us was Frankenstein, which I’m pretty sure was a thinly-veiled analogy.

How do you convince the world that you’re not a monster, when they decide with a single glance?

The scientists decided it would make a difference mentally for us to bond, and to see them as people. A program was launched to talk to a human via text chat, no videos or images. Their appearance was the stuff of nightmares, so it was easier to start without that in mind.

Out of morbid curiosity, and perhaps some pity for Frankenstein’s wretch, I had volunteered. The human I spoke to was named Marcel. He was a soldier with a dry sense of humor, a passion for environmental causes, and a philosophical mind. Against the odds, I liked him; we became inseparable. I confided my deepest thoughts, and learned a great deal about Terran life in return.

We finally docked. God, that was terrifying, Marcel texted. Longest four hours of my life.

It’ll be worth it. I’m excited to meet you, I replied.

Me too, bud. I know it won’t be easy for you. If you need space, or it’s too much, please tell me.

I will.

After weeks of distant communication, the final phase was exposure therapy. The plan was for us to room with our human counterpart for several days. I would be alone with a predator with no escape. They said once you got past the first few hours, the nerves would settle down. We needed to get used to the humans, if they were ever to be accepted.

What do you think I look like? Marcel asked. In your head?

I don’t know. I try not to think about it.

Why not? You know what humans look like from TV.

Well, it’s weird to think that you’re a predator. That you look at a dead animal, all that blood and guts, and think, ‘Hey, that’s food.’

I’m a vegetarian, Slanek. Not applicable.

Gah…not you specifically. I mean humans in general. The fact that you’re wired to think that’s appetizing. To kill other animals for a meal.

It’s not like that but…it’s just evolution. Biology sucks.

It does. I guess I’ll know what you look like soon, Marcel.

Yep. A face only a mother could love.

I snorted, amused in spite of myself. The clicking of boots down the hall meant the humans were in the building; there were mere seconds to brace myself. I switched off my holopad, and tried to regulate my breathing. We were allowing enough of them in to handily overtake this space station, if they were to try. These were social predators, so perhaps encouraging them to travel in packs wasn’t the best idea…

The door swung open; I was flabbergasted by the imposing wall of muscle that entered. Something deep in my subconscious howled at the sight of a predator, blocking my only escape route. Startling hazel eyes scanned my figure, and my breath hitched in my throat. Marcel’s lips twitched for a moment, and I could tell from how he pursed them he didn’t want to smile. We had been warned repeatedly about the humans’ teeth-baring display of friendliness.

“Slanek.” The voice was harsh and raspy, as though he was gargling saltwater. “I know the feeling’s not mutual, but God, you’re adorable.”

I gritted my teeth, trying not to back away. “T-thanks. C-come in.”

The human saw that I had set my belongings on the bottom bunk, and tossed his duffel bag on top. Well, this isn’t that bad, I thought. There had been no sudden movements, he was keeping his distance, and he didn’t have the razor teeth of the Arxur. With his back to me, I couldn’t see his piercing eyes. All positives. My heart was hammering in my chest, but I had kept myself together.

“Jeesh, I’m starving,” the human announced, as he began to unpack.

There were few words I would’ve liked to hear less. Isolated in close quarters with a hungry “vegetarian” predator…aw fuck, why had I signed up for this? The nearest meal was obviously me. I skittered backward on instinct, trying to shield my throat.

Marcel frowned. “I was just going to suggest that we grab a bite together. Or, uh, I brought snacks. We can share.”

“Sorry,” I squeaked.

The human retrieved a plastic bag from his belongings, and popped it open with a single tug. He withdrew a yellow wafer, shoving it down his gullet. As he turned the bag to face me, I eyed the offering suspiciously.

“It’s a potato chip,” he said, before I could ask. “Baked from a Terran plant.”

Did I trust the predator enough to consume his foodstuff? How did I know it wasn’t dried animal fat? I tried to remind myself that this was my friend. The one who gave me relationship advice and told silly jokes. My stomach squirmed as I grasped a chip, but I placed it in my mouth anyways. It was salty and starchy, yet strangely addictive.

My ears twitched with pleasant surprise. “That’s good.”

“Isn’t it?” Marcel mumbled, through a mouthful of food. “I figure we could use some carbs, before these…ugh, experiments you want us in.”

“They mentioned something about that. It’s psychological research, isn’t it?”

“I don’t know. Your scientists just mentioned it was a test. The UN signed off on it, so I’d hope it’s ethical.”

“They probably just want to be sure you don’t want to eat us.”

“I’ll pass with flying colors then. Not sure where the lab is though.”

“Uh, I’ll take you there.”

“Great. Let’s get it over with, shall we?”

Once the fright began to subside, speaking to Marcel felt less forced. It tickled my instincts, but not in a way my conscious brain couldn’t override. A little discomfort was nothing I couldn’t handle. It wasn’t like he had actually done anything to threaten me, or diverged from his online persona in a noticeable way. Chatting via text was easier, but it was unfair to ostracize the humans forever. The predators had been understanding enough as things were.

Unless any red flags were uncovered in their psychological screening, Terran soldiers would accompany Venlil ships on today’s mid-rotation patrols. It was possible UN Peacekeepers would remain as permanent fixtures in our crew. In that case, I would be relieved to have a conclusive answer on the workings of the human mind. Predators were known to toy with their prey in nature. The more intelligent they were, the more sadistic and deceptive they could be.

I tried not to think about what I would do, if I found out Marcel’s niceties were a long con. There were a few humans present at the lab, probably to monitor the methods used for research. Sara, who I recognized as a lingering visitor from the UN first contact team, was hunched over a microscope. She seemed to be analyzing some cell samples with a Venlil scientist, and waved at us as we entered.

“Welcome!” How Sara sensed us, with her lack of peripheral vision, was beyond me. “Here for the behavioral exam?”

“Uh, yep. I think,” my roommate grumbled.

“Excellent. Just sign the consent form, and then speak to Ilja here.” Sara gestured toward the Venlil hovering beside her. “Don’t worry. It’ll be quick.”

Marcel hesitated before scrawling his name on the dotted line. I noted how thin and frail his fingers looked, for a predator; they were like spindly twigs. Either my imagination was running amok, or his hands quivered as he set the pen down. The humans looked terrifying to us, but I couldn’t picture them going toe-to-toe with the Arxur.

Before the ink dried on his signature, Ilja was strapping Marcel to a chair. The restraints seemed excessive for a consensual test. Electrodes were fastened to his skull, and his shirt was removed to tape a series of wires to his chest. Clips placed on his fingers fed additional data to a vitals monitor. I noticed the human growing more agitated, the more equipment he was hooked up to. The rise and fall of his chest had quickened dramatically.

“Don’t leave, Slanek. Please,” he pleaded. “This is making me nervous as hell.”

A sympathetic ache filled my chest cavity. It was strange to think that the predator was afraid of us, but I hated seeing a friend in distress. What were our scientists testing, exactly? Guarantees were necessary to cement trust in these creatures, but I was worried about what would be done to achieve that. It looked as though they were planning to elicit a violent reaction from Marcel. Human subjects deserved proper treatment, not to be goaded into retaliation.

Why do I feel so protective of him? I mused. I haven’t known him that long.

“It’s going to be okay, Marc.” I waved my tail reassuringly. “They won’t hurt you. I promise.”

The human furrowed his brow. “But you’ll stay?”

“Of course. I’ll be here.”

Marcel relaxed, and the twinge in my chest deepened. The sentiments I felt in this moment suggested that, despite the inherent risk, it was possible to grow attached to a predator. Whether humanity was sincere in its friendship, or if that was a one-sided delusion, remained to be seen.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 41
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [Standardized human time]:
October 8, 2136

When the science officer from humanity's first contact team reached out about a fear study, I was a bit intimidated. Sara Rosario had done extensive biological and environmental analysis, and collaborated with Venlil scientists throughout their early behavioral research. Her talks comparing our psychology racked up millions of views, as did her controversial analysis on Venlil ecosystems.

In a nutshell, Terran "conservationists" were less than thrilled with our biome manipulation. Sara had lambasted our efforts to wipe out predator species, and discussed something she referred to as "trophic cascades". The aspects she attributed to the absence of hunters were far-fetched, though she spoke at length about supposed examples from Earth.

How could removing a terrestrial predator alter the ocean, destroy vegetation, or spread diseases? Humans can prove their own worth without grasping at straws; these arguments are just moronic.

Besides her fringe theories, Sara was a remarkable scientist, with credentials in several fields. If anyone could find a way to break Venlil fear responses, it would be her. I knew the process could be traumatic, but I would do anything to leave my internalized feelings behind once and for all. I was tired of failing to protect my human friends.

"Are you sure about this, Slanek?" Marcel growled, as we approached the scientist. "If you're trying to be more human to appease me, please don't. I accept you for you."

I squeezed my tail around his wrist. "Thanks, but I'm doing this for myself. I'm tired of being scared, and at the whims of my instincts."

Tyler patted me on the back, a little harder than I would've liked. The blond human accompanied our group to assist with any physical activities, since Marcel was still in recovery from his gunshot wounds. The UN military was involved with these experiments, so I knew part of it was seeing if I could be shaped into a proper soldier. Dread festered already, knowing simulated combat was in my future.

"Why do you keep helping me, Tyler? We haven't known each other long, and you must have other things to do," I said.

"Dude, I wanted to be in the buddy program, just like you two. The UN turned me down." The soldier towered over me, and his blue eyes glittered like ice crystals. "They didn't think I would mesh with the Venlil, I guess. Too tall and too scary."

Marcel frowned. "You were turned down 'cause you're not vegetarian. Though your stature probably doesn't help your case."

"Aliens are the most exciting thing to ever happen to mankind. I want to be a part of this all, but maybe they were right. I always stick my foot in my mouth with the Venlil."

I studied the flesh-eating soldier, imagining I had never seen a human before. Marcel was a daunting hunk of muscle when I first glimpsed him. His shadow smothered me, and his forward-facing eyes were like spotlights peering down from above. It was only seeing him at his most vulnerable, cold and afraid, that squashed that threatening aura.

That said, my friend barely came up to Tyler's shoulders. The sandy-haired soldier was tall, even by human standards. His dietary choices would've given everyone at the outpost the creeps. It was likely something would be blurted out about dogs and persistence hunting, at a stage when his partner wasn't ready to accept that.

Still, there were a lot of good memories to be formed with Tyler, if you could see past the bulky predator. He was friendly to a fault, considering my emotions at times when I was harsher than he deserved. There was selflessness in the way he didn't hesitate to carry me off the cradle. I hoped other Venlil would give him a chance someday.

I nuzzled against his arm, which startled the big guy. "I appreciate you, Tyler; your heart is in the right place. Don't give up. Appearances aren't everything."

"That was actually… sensitive and thoughtful." Marcel feigned a gasp, and I giggled as the whites of his eyes expanded to cartoonish dimensions. "Who are you, and what have you done with Slanek?"

"Oh, shut up! You humans are a lot to take in, and you know it!"

Tyler placed a hand on his hip, striking a goofy pose. "Well, take it all in, buddy. Appearances are worth something. 210 pounds of glorious, rugged—"

"Yeah, yeah, you're the pinnacle of male perfection," Marcel snorted, shoving the other soldier with his good arm. "Keep walking! The Secretary-General doesn't want to see that."

The Secretary-General? Why would Meier be here?

I followed my human's gaze, and surveyed the Terran scientists camped by the machines. Sara was taking an inventory of her equipment, while other predators were staring at us. My nerves flared, as I realized most humans present were in military uniforms. I knew these experiments would have combat applications, but I didn't think martial leaders were calling the shots.

Secretary-General Meier looked less amused with my pack's antics than I was; tomfoolery was not his favorite pastime. He was in a heated discussion with several people in green-and-brown uniforms. The color scheme looked like a tree threw up on it, but they didn't seem the type that would appreciate such comments.

Sara waved us over to her. "Long time no see, Slanek. Glad you're back in one piece."

"Uh, I'm hoping to s-stay that way? Why are all these important pred...humans here?" I squeaked.

She lowered her eyes. "There's no easy way to say this, but I'm afraid our work will have to move much faster than I anticipated. We don't have much time."

"You heard the news from Venlil Prime?" Secretary-General Meier interjected.

Marcel nodded. "We did. Ambassador Williams is alive, and he returned with some new friends."

I was glad my human piped up, because this ambush had thrown me off my prepared responses. Was this about helping our new allies with their own first contact programs? Maybe trying to create an easier bonding process?

"The picture of the Zorlin—" Tyler began.

"Zurulian," Sara and I corrected at the same time.

"—Zurulian on the human's shoe is everywhere. My man was just like, 'Oh, a predator?' Looks like a warm, comfy pillow to me."

Secretary Meier breathed an irritated sigh. "The other news. The Krakotl are leading a crusade against us, and we have less friends than foes. Not that even our 'friends' are likely to help. Simple math dictates that we're at a numerical disadvantage."

"The thousands of ships the birds've been massing represent a multi-species coalition," one of the uniformed personnel chimed in. "Projections indicate that they'll set sail today, and arrive on October 16th or 17th."

Horror coursed through my veins, as the gravity of the Terrans' revelations set in. How could these humans be so calm at the prospect of an attack on Earth? Marcel and Tyler both were subdued, but their reaction wasn't on the level it should be. This was a raid with the intention of turning their verdant home into a barren rock; the same as the Arxur's vile tactics.

The Krakotl were one of the few species that could head a functional offensive. They boasted a high aggression, since they evolved to scare off predators. During the initial phases of the Arxur war, the avians conjured up the technology that allowed us to regroup. While nobody was on the humans' level, they possessed some tactical acumen.

"W-why not launch a pre-emptive strike? Like you did with the Gojids?" I demanded.

Meier frowned. "It's too late now, but it wouldn't have worked. Most of their ships were already space-borne, so we couldn't catch them sleeping like the Gojids. They concentrated forces around their stations heavily."

"But you're excellent fighters. You have advanced ships now. Nobody can rival a predator's military prowess."

"They outnumbered us ten-to-one, if we sent the entirety of our fledgling armada. They also had home-turf advantage, and orbital lasers around every base. You might as well launch the UN fleet into a supernova; you'd get the same results."

Sara sighed. "Our best hope was for Noah to convince them to stand down. That didn't work out."

I turned my gaze toward Marcel, noticing how his gaze drifted to his holopad. My human's thoughts were transparent at times. He was worried about the welfare of Nulia and Lucy, who remained back at his residence. The Gojid child would never feel safe again, if she watched another world endure destruction.

That's if anyone survives the attack on Earth. The entire human race is in jeopardy, I realized. We need to get everyone off-world, before it's too late.

I pinned my ears against my head. "You know the Krakotl are coming. There's still time. Evacuate Earth!"

"And go where? Anyone who wishes to leave will have the opportunity, including you," the Secretary-General growled.

"This is our home; we've built everything here. It's the only planet we've got." Marcel ruffled the stray tuft on my head, gentle and reassuring as ever. "Us soldiers, we're going to stay and fight."

"No!" I shrieked. "Come with me to Venlil territory. We'll take care of you…all of you. Please, don't die, humans."

"It's okay, buddy. Go back to your world. I want you to be safe."

Tears rolled down my face, at the thought of Marcel perishing by a Krakotl horde. It brought back unwanted memories; like the scorching pain in my chest, when I thought he was about to be shot in front of me. We had been to hell and back together, and it had finally seemed like our lives could settle down.

Now, without warning, the light at the end of the tunnel was extinguished. If Sara's team were cancelling my experiment, I understood. Humans had bigger things to worry about than my fragile instincts.

"Scrap the study. It's not a priority." I rubbed a paw against my cheek, catching the water rolling down my fur. "You don't have to worry about diplomatic fallout from me. I want to fight with you."

Meier shook his head. "We can discuss integration to a UN vessel, if the results of your training are positive. However, I recommend that you lend that option some serious thought, as high casualties are expected."

"I appreciate that humans honor your word, but you do not have time to fix me. Don't waste—"

"This study is very important, Slanek, for the survival of our species." The Secretary-General crossed his arms, a calculating scowl on his face. "Look, if Earth falls, the Venlil will be custodians of the few remaining humans. It will be up to you to rebuild our population, and to protect our survivors from threats."

"Don't talk like that. Please!"

"I have to. Our research could point you in the right direction, and make your soldiers stronger."

"If things don't work out for us, this is humanity's parting gift," Sara finished. "I speak for all of us in saying that I hope the Venlil prosper."

My tail drooped between my legs, and it was all I could do not to collapse in defeat. The Terrans' odds of defending such an onslaught were slim; every human I knew could be dead in little over a week. Hearing the UN leader speak as if that probability was likely, crushed my hopes that the Sol system had some predatory tricks tucked away. Their species didn't deserve this fate.

The humans faced their impending doom with fearlessness, so I needed to accept reality too. If my participation strengthened the Venlil military in the UN's absence, I would do whatever was asked of me. No matter the mental duress this exacted on me, it was worth it.

I swallowed hard. "Thanks for telling me yourself, sir. Where do we begin?"

Sara rummaged through a box of her belongings, and retrieved a red fabric sleeve. It took all of my willpower not to shy away as she tugged it over my face. Her curved nails waded through my fur like daggers. I couldn't see at all for a split second, which added to the panic. How could placing coverings on my head impart anything?

They have to have a good reason. These predators will not hurt you. Humans will never hurt you, I repeated internally.

The human scientist was gentle as she tugged a pair of straps behind my ears. My vision returned, as two cutouts fell over the eyes' positioning. It felt like I was suffocating in the mask, but the fit was correct enough. Was it custom-made to my dimensions? Its purpose must lie beyond adding color to my silver fur.

I realized that something was wrong with my sight, as soon as I processed my surroundings. Where I had seen Tyler standing beside me, there was only a dark shadow. Marcel's comforting snarl was obscured as well. This headgear had barriers to take away my periphery. Was this what it was like, to have predator sight?

Sara clapped her hands. "Perfect."

"You good, Slanek?" Marcel's voice echoed from my left, and I had to turn my head to look at him. The motion felt alien. "You look miserable…like a fish out of water."

It was tough to describe how it felt, to be unaware of the objects in my vicinity. Simply carrying out a conversation was unnatural. No wonder humans got jumpy, if I came up beside them without thinking. Something could sneak up behind me now, and I wouldn't realize it was there until it pounced.

"I'll survive," I grumbled. "You're going to make me calmer, Sara, by limiting my vision? No offense, but I thought limited optical range was a downside to being human."

"Your instincts are triggered by things approaching from the side or behind you. You're easily distracted by your surroundings, because you see too much at once. I think this'll help your spook reflex, to focus on a single target at a time."

"I get it. Like horse blinders," Tyler stated, in a glummer tone than usual.

Like what? Maybe I'm making the wrong inference again, but it sounds like they've tried to force their tunnel vision on other prey animals.

The scientist nodded. "Precisely. Slanek, why don't we try a combat simulator with the blinders? If it doesn't help, or you really don't like it, we'll drop it."

"Fine."

Sara steered me into a separate room with a light touch. The enclosed space appeared to be an imitation of a patrol ship cabin, complete with controls and sensor readouts. Where the viewport should sit, there were blank screens; I imagined they would reflect Arxur ships in a few minutes.

Tyler squeezed into the copilot's seat, a downcast expression on his face. The tall human knew we could be in a dogfight that was very real, a short time from now. The stakes of our next mission would be his entire planet.

This flight presented no tangible threat, and I needed to keep that fact at the forefront of my mind. Somewhere deep inside my soul, there had to be some bravery lurking. All that mattered was gaining admission to the UN's last stand, and proving that prey genetics didn't define us.

These virtual enemies were going to have hell to pay.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 47
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Kalsim,
Krakotl Alliance Command

Date [standardized human time]:
October 16, 2136

When deprived of sleep for days, the crew began to get a little jumpy. The Terran ambushes became more sporadic along the journey, but persisted all the same. The Krakotl fleet was left with no choice but to stay on constant alert. I focused on keeping the other officers rested, while I shouldered the brunt of the shifts. My personnel became run-down despite the adjustment.

It was severe enough that I ordered Zarn to give essential crew members stimulants. The drugs left me wired enough that my wing wouldn’t stop twitching, which was a nuisance. But with our arrival slated for today, the soldiers couldn’t afford to be drowsy. Sharp wits were a necessity to clash with humans; perhaps that was the purpose of the ambushes all along.

Yet another disruptor pulse had shaken us up on the outskirts of the Sol System. The jarring effects were becoming routine, as we all tried to clear the fog from our minds. My eyes felt like a Mazic was sitting on them, but I forced them to stay open. The predators wouldn’t break us on my watch, not on the cusp of our destination.

My gaze shifted to the viewport. “XO, status report.”

“I’m detecting sensor anomalies. The humans may be somewhere nearby, but it’s tough to tell.” Thyon proved a godsend with his analytical mind. His skillset complimented my tactical understanding. “We’re already in the system’s outer orbit. This is their last chance to strike.”

The sensor readout revealed that we were less than a milliparsec from Earth. We anticipated the bulk of the Terran armada was waiting within Sol’s inner reaches. I had no doubt the humans set up FTL interference throughout their system, so there would be no further hyperspace hops. The rest of the journey could be handled sublight.

Our instruments picked up millions of planetesimals, which were mainly composed of ice. The circumstellar disc was a sprawling collection, which Federation scientists had noted as one of two debris planes. Our fleet filtered out all water-dominant objects, so they wouldn’t drown out enemy movement.

Where are the humans? If this is the border of their territory, you think they’d send someone to greet us.

“Is there anything to be concerned about with this location? Any weapons hidden in the belt?” I squawked.

The first officer cleared his throat. “The objects are spread too far apart to pose a threat, sir…as visual indicates. I detect no mining activity or research stations.”

“There has to be something unusual,” I pressed. “Humans don’t just pick their spots at random.”

“All I notice is that they just powered down the FTL disruptors. Perhaps their primitive defenses are malfunctioning? We could shave a few hours from our travel time, if we can get in one more jump.”

Suspicion filtered through my tired brain, and I urged myself to consider the circumstances. It seemed unlikely that all of humanity’s defenses would collapse at the same time. The only reason they would halt the signal would be to allow their own ships through. But there were no unknown drive signatures on sensors. We should see any predators coming with ease.

As if to mock my certainty, a massive chunk of ice blinked into existence amidst Krakotl ranks. It plowed into the heart of our formation, dwarfing the ships it steamrolled over. Panicked chatter barked over the radio, and our Federation allies scrambled to expend an orbital bomb on the object. We managed to crack the first planetesimal, but dozens more surfaced on several headings.

My talons undid the sensors’ filter, and hundreds of warp blips emerged on my screen. The predators predicted that we would filter out anything icy, which rendered their strike invisible to our instruments. I could appreciate the deviousness of their ploy; human creativity was leaps and bounds beyond the Arxur.

I leaned over the comms panel. “ALL FEDERATION VESSELS, deploy your FTL disruptors now!”

The subspace indicators vanished, as enough of our allies complied with my order. Still, dozens of hijacked planetoids, twenty times the diameter of our craft, were enough to cause a headache. We needed to take evasive maneuvers if any were on trajectory for our position.

Jala puffed out her chest with excitement. “And so it begins. I want to be the one to push the button when we burn their cities!”

There was no time to worry about her derangement. It didn’t matter if she was the one dropping the payload, or if I handled it myself. As the one giving the orders, the burden of responsibility fell on me. I knew what a terrible deed we were about to commit; the mental images gnawed at my conscience.

At least the creatures from past exterminations had no foreknowledge of their demise. I wondered how many humans’ last thoughts would be of their families. Those unsightly hunters had more in common with us than most Krakotl would like to admit. Their desperation to survive and their collectivism resonated with our own.

It is truly a shame that predators are prone to destruction and violence. There is only room for one of us in the galaxy, I reminded myself. This crew is sacrificing something of ourselves, so that the Federation has a chance to survive.

Nonetheless, I respected how the hominids utilized every asset at their disposal. Dozens of Krakotl warships lie crushed or totaled around us; the Terrans never had to rear their ugly heads. One icy object was barreling toward our location, despite the pitiful attempts to obliterate it. The asteroid’s magnitude left no doubts that our hull would implode, if it connected.

“The damn inbreds strapped a warp drive to a space rock. Who the fuck does that? Or even thinks to do that?!” Thyon spat.

I hummed in thought. “Someone who sees anything as a potential weapon. A predator much more dangerous than the Arxur.”

The Farsul gritted his teeth. “Glad you’ve seen the light, Captain.”

“I’ve always ‘seen the light.’ Now quit with your snide remarks, and find us a way out of this mess!”

Thyon jerked his floppy ears in disdain, before issuing new orders to navigations. The asteroid was propelled forward by its existing momentum. It was near enough that I could glimpse the imperfections on its surface. Distant sunlight glinted off the watery composite, and washed it in a serene, ultraviolet hue. That color would look a lot less beautiful smashed up against our plating.

Our vessel executed a sharp turn, and rerouted power to acceleration. The state-of-the-art warship didn’t seem to cover the space fast enough; it felt like a predator was nipping at our talons. My stomach somersaulted, as the projectile scraped by nearly atop us. We cleared the collision course with mere seconds to spare.

The humans might’ve hoped to incite panic, so that they could cow us through our instincts. We had to remember that the stakes were our entire civilization; our right to roam the galaxy in freedom and dignity. Quelling my nerves, I contemplated which weaponry could take the icy mass out. Careful placement of explosives should still conserve firepower for the main event.

Movement flashed in the viewport’s corner, a streaking blur of metal. My weary brain took a full second to process the new data. An allied vessel was gunning straight toward us; a head-on collision wasn’t something either of us would survive. But the fools were preoccupied dodging their own asteroid, and seemed oblivious to our presence.

“Move the blasted ship!” I screeched. “Can you not see we’re going to crash?!”

The navigations officer curled his neck with trepidation, as he frantically brought our nose upward. There was a brief scraping sound, from the friendly brushing our underbelly. The artificial gravity failed to compensate for another abrupt change. A forceful tug sucked us toward the rear of the bridge, and I lost my balance on my perch.

My wings fluttered frantically. There wasn’t enough time to gain proper lift, but I wanted to slow my fall. The air beneath my cyan feathers allowed me to drift, and I glided down the slanted gravity well. Other Krakotl also used shared instincts to cushion their fall.

Thyon wasn’t as fortunate; flight didn’t exactly grace his tubby form. The Farsul’s stout paws offered little traction, and his curved hindlegs made his bipedal stance… precarious in the best circumstances. His jowls quivered with fear as he tumbled backward. There was a sickening crack from his head slamming against the support wall.

“Thyon! XO, you will answer when I speak to you! Give me some sign that you’re alright,” I hollered.

The first officer didn’t respond. He was crumpled in a limp heap, with a concerning amount of blood pooling around him. What if the poor guy was dead? Regardless of his attitude, the last thing I wanted was to send him home in a body bag.

Jala clicked her beak together in delight, and I shot her a warning look. She was elated that my second was knocked out of commission, since it cleared the return of her old post. It was bothersome that a person could derive pleasure from another’s misfortune, but I suppose it was no different than Zarn relishing human suffering. Soldiers like them could perform their duties without remorse, at least.

Focus on the battle, I chided myself. You cannot get distracted and let the humans surprise you again. Honor Thyon’s wishes.

The gravity adjustment kicked in at last, and my crew members scrambled back to their posts. The navigations officer rushed to level our heading. We were fortunate to escape with our frame intact, and only a few dozen allies taken out. The most imaginative strategist wouldn’t have accounted for asteroids warping out of nowhere.

I glided over to the downed first officer, containing any untoward displays of grief. His russet fur was matted with blood, and he was unresponsive to poking. My talons locked around his hind ankle, digging into the pulse point. Relief coursed through my veins, as I felt a faint heartbeat.

“Doctor Zarn!” I sent a transmission to the medical bay, praying that the spiteful Takkan had any healing aptitude. “My security team is transporting the first officer to your lab. Serious head trauma, internal bleeding.”

“Understood. I’ll attend to the necessary preparations, Captain,” Zarn replied.

The security personnel carted the unconscious Farsul away, and I suppressed my concern. With neural trauma, the officer might be looking at permanent damage even if he was stabilized. There was no telling what timeframe to expect for Thyon’s recovery, but I doubted he’d be back within the mission’s span. It hadn’t been within my forecast to lose anyone this early in the mission.

My attention reluctantly returned to the battlefield, where the Federation fleet was trying to regroup. Dormant Terran ships crept out from behind planetoids, and descended on any stragglers who strayed too far from the group. The chaos of the asteroids had broken our tight formation. Numbers were our primary advantage; we would be fine as long as we stuck together.

They cannot stop all of us, or even a majority.

Jala ordered a sizable contingent of our fleet to charge at the Terran raiders, to deter them from pressing their luck. I blinked in irritation, as she claimed that the command was authorized by me. Lying was not a quality I appreciated, especially when it was done to get her way quickly. Then again, perhaps it was better to let her make the time-sensitive decisions.

“Burn any humans that try to run! We have to kill every one of them!” Jala shrieked.

The atmosphere was solemn, as her phraseology was a bit too honest. She projected a certain vindictiveness that needed to be tempered down. This mission couldn’t be about inflicting suffering, or killing for killing’s sake. That was not why I wanted my crew to think we were doing this.

I tucked my wings behind my back. “Don’t let a single predator go, if you can stop it. The more humans that escape, the greater the chance they retain a viable population.”

“Why is that such a bad thing, sir?” an engineering assistant asked.

“There’s two futures, son: the one where we survive, and the one where they do. When cancer metastasizes, it infects and consumes all healthy tissue nearby,” I answered. “Is that what you want for the galaxy? Consider this an early detection…before it spreads to our heart.”

A group of Terran fighters were blazing away, after punching at our weakest links. To my relief, my crew locked onto a pair of targets and chased them with plasma. Krakotl warships converged on the cluster like locusts; they sent those “fearless hunters” running off like Venlil.

The humans were surprisingly slippery, finding an escape route with minimal casualties. Their ships evaded with vaulting maneuvers, and a plethora of defensive countermeasures were built into their hardware. For all my knowledge of predators, I hadn’t expected these ones to be so adept at fleeing. This was a positive sign, if they had so little courage.

My eyes landed on the faint blue dot on the horizon, which the predatory opportunists were retreating toward. Humanity was poised to make their last stand; the poor saps would perish without any reason to be missed. We were close enough to Earth to detect thousands of ship contacts, fanned out as a protective ward. A smarter species would’ve used those vessels to flee, if they knew of our arrival.

That territorial nature does have its downsides. They’d rather fight and die, just like we predicted.

The first wave of Terran defenses were beaten, and I suspected that was the toughest stage of transit. That asteroid trick would only work once. We had a clean shot to the predator’s home. Now, that small fleet was all that stood between us and orbital supremacy.

We were so close to eliminating the menace that was humanity.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 95
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
December 4, 2136

The memories trickled through my brain, as a deep chill rattled my body. I was disoriented and immobile, uncertain of my surroundings. The current time and location were indeterminable; haziness obscured my conscious thoughts. My mind reached out for context, in an attempt to ground myself.

We had been caged in the Tilfish nursery; I was shot during the fray. Marcel had propped me up, ignoring the strain on his own body. Orange blood flowed onto his chest pelt, and perspiration beads coated his skin. Dino tagged along, whimpering as my eyes began to turn glassy. Virnt was back in Birla’s arms, asking why the Venlil was leaking.

We were a ragtag band, stranded on Sillis. I remembered now.

The grays had been hot on our heels, and we hobbled toward the emergency exit. My vision was fixed on the floor tiles, which were mired with my dripping blood. General Birla urged Virnt to cover his ears, as she dispensed my firearm at the Arxur. I think the carnivores refrained from gunning us down, because they wanted to capture us alive.

There was more. We had to get to the emergency exit, didn’t we? Why is it all slipping out of reach?

“Shoot me,” I had coughed at Marcel. “Save yourselves…please, brother.”

The predator refused to let go, bending his arm tighter around my torso. Tiredness threatened to consume me, as the vegetarian popped errant shots over his shoulder. Images flitted through my brain, from various moments of time; that forced snarl was his classic empathy rendition. That same expression had consoled me when Sovlin held him at gunpoint.

Not too long ago, I’d been feeding the half-dead Terran by hand. Amid the chaos, I recalled hoping that Marcel knew how much I cared about his welfare. There were terrible screams, both near and afar, which sent my heart pounding. Despite all of the nightmares we had endured, I wouldn’t change a thing about our partnership. Even if Marcel was losing patience with me, I hoped he still felt our bond.

Think Slanek. The screams. There was something there.

Those had been Tilfish screams, as the incubator workers came running in droves. Our hasty escape hadn’t given me time to don blinders; I’d seen it all. The civilians distracted our Arxur pursuers, stampeding past them at full speed. As much as the grays wanted a Venlil delicacy, this easy meal toppled into their laps.

Our ragtag band stumbled out into fresh air, and I was wholly leaning on Marcel for support. There were more Arxur in the street. I think that was the memory in its entirety; I’d glued the pieces back together. We needed to find somewhere to take cover…to take…

Birla clicked her mandibles in the backdrop. “Slanek? Slanek, you have to keep your eyes open.”

I drew a gasping breath, and my pupils snapped to my arm. Judging by the dark hue and the profuse leakage, the bullet hit a vein. There was a wet sensation on my hindlegs; at first, I worried it was blood from my wound. However, the realization that the brick tunnel we were in was a rotting mess ensued. A few inches of murky liquid amassed across the floor. Perhaps this was a sewer system underground?

My addled brain shook off the stupor, and I searched for Marcel’s comforting presence. I scanned every shadow for the lurking human. This wasn’t the first time the predator had been around my blood, so I knew that he could handle the alluring scent. On Sovlin’s ship, I’d been immobile with a head wound, and locked in an enclosed cell without food. Even then, the human had cared about my welfare.

There was no reason a vegetarian who loved rescuing animals should need to get away from blood. Humans weren’t drawn to it like the Arxur; I’d never seen them react positively to a whiff of it. That ruled out that explanation for why my friend was missing. What if Marcel had gotten hurt? I couldn’t remember how we made it down here at all.

“Why are we not going to space with humma?” Virnt wailed.

Birla patted him soothingly. “Shh, darling. Go back to bed.”

Dino is missing as well. What if the dog ate Marcel? Or…I guess more likely, the grays got them both.

“Where…is M-marc?” I pressed one paw against the wall, and tried to sit upright. “How did we get here?”

The Tilfish general blinked with concern. “You don’t remember? The human carried you into an access hatch, and checked that it was clear. He put you down, told me to patch you up…but I don’t have anything for first aid!”

“Okay. Where is he now?”

“Said something about hearing Arxur in the tunnels. Took that feral quadruped—”

“Dino, mama!” Virnt cheered. “Dino the dog!”

“Yes, that thing. Anyways, Marcel went looking for enemies. Mentioned clearing the tunnels, and keeping us safe.”

“And you let him go alone?”

“The human said to stay with you. He was blinking a lot…I’m not sure if your blood bothered him.”

“It would never. M-marc was upset that I’m hurt, if anything.”

“Are you sure, Slanek?”

“Of course I’m sure! He was fine around a Gojid stampede. They all…the humans all were. He saved…a trampled child.”

There was a long pause, as skepticism swam in the Tilfish general’s eyes. I knew the insectoid wouldn’t ditch Marcel, when the primate was our best asset against the Arxur. But I suppose few individuals beside myself would tempt a predator’s bloodlust. It took personal exposure to humanity’s nurturing side to accept that their empathy dominated.

Marcel said himself that he doesn’t like killing. Humans can balance empathy and violence; it’s what I told him at the supply tent.

A gunshot exchange sounded down the tunnel, and fear clenched at my heart. The adrenaline boosted me back to alertness, but I couldn’t stand up. Bootsteps smacked the floor, alongside the sound of munitions chipping bricks. A human yowl reverberated through the structure, followed by Dino’s throaty barks. Tears swelled in my eyes, realizing Marcel would die alone.

I reached out to Birla, and pulled myself up with the last of my strength. Hunched over at the waist, I staggered in the direction of my friend’s cry. The Tilfish general tried to grab my shoulder, flinching away as blood coated her leg. With a frustrated grunt, I hobbled down the tunnel. It wasn’t long before I was leaning against the wall for support.

“FUCK OFF!” That was Marcel’s thunderous voice. It was possible to discern the words in this roar, which was more formidable than any I’d heard before. “This is my turf! You’re not coming in here, assholes!”

My legs buckled, and I crumpled back onto the floor. Why hadn’t I reclaimed my firearm? The coldness was becoming palpable, making me wish for a human pelt to cocoon myself in. At least Marcel was still fighting, but I was in no state to rescue him. My pupils fluttered in his direction, as I sucked in some wheezing breaths.

The human was hugging a wall corner, and I could see his teeth flash from here. His hands popped off a few shots, while enemy rounds buffeted his refuge. Brick debris sprinkled overhead, as Marcel clutched his gun tighter. Dino was growling at his side, though the mutt appeared to be waiting for something.

“Surrender yourself, human! We have room for an honorable prisoner,” a bone-chilling voice called out.

A maniacal laugh emanated from Marcel. “What is it with aliens, drawing my name in the ‘kidnapping and torture’ lottery? I’ll pass.”

I crawled along the floor, moving a few inches at a time. Since I was wounded anyways, my best usage was to serve as a distraction. The Arxur might wish to collect me as cattle, and that could give Marcel the clear shot he needed. The chances of us surviving Sillis were slim overall, but the Terran would fare better without my dead weight.

Scuttling noises echoed behind me, and Birla came racing down the hallway. The Tilfish general righted my seized firearm, angling it toward the Arxur. Despite her distrust, she was willing to come to the human's aid. In my opinion, she should’ve gone with him to begin with…better late than never, I suppose.

Three Arxur ducked around the corner, just as Birla halved the distance. The insectoid had a trusty shot, clocking one gray in the brain. Marcel released Dino upon the hostiles, and depressed his trigger. Enemy bullets answered, taking out a brick right above his head. I could feel his adrenaline vicariously; his binocular eyes were crazed.

I have to help somehow. The Slanek acting weak distraction seemed to work the last time…should I try it again?

“Yummy Venlil! Over here!” I cried out, with a faltering voice.

The Arxur had already scented my blood, I assumed. The trail must’ve drawn them down here, unless they followed us from the surface. It was possible they waited for us to lower our guard. While I’d technically been conscious in our travels, it was tough to retrieve the memories. There was a chance I wouldn’t remember any of this now.

The two surviving grays weren’t as distracted as the egg raiders had been, but I saw their pupils twitch. The lack of impulse control was in stark contrast to humans; I suppose I was lucky that Isif and his bunch didn’t wolf me down in New York. A little blood or a wounded animal’s cry worked their kind into a frenzy, even amidst combat.

Marcel cursed, realizing I’d abandoned my refuge. The human popped up from his crouch, and the grays rushed to shoot him. One bullet whizzed dangerously close to his earlobe, while additional shots lurked in the chamber. The lead Arxur’s sights aligned with his temples; I felt my blood pressure plummet. Was that from my wounds, or just grief?

“NO!” I screamed.

There was nothing I could do to stop the bullet from piercing his brain. The Terran had become reckless out of concern for me, and he was paying the ultimate price. Marcel managed to take down one gray, in a final act of defiance. The next thing I heard was a deafening boom, as the monster shot my best friend.

The predator’s head snapped back with unnatural speed, and he crashed onto his back. I screamed as the human lie splayed out on the floor. Dragging myself on all fours, my toes bled from the frantic pace. My frayed vocal cords screeched his name, while warm tears ran down my face. The grief I felt was a chasm in my chest, an all-consuming sadness.

Birla dispatched the final Arxur, and scuttled over to Marcel’s side. I managed to reach the predator’s body, which was still warm to my touch. It was tough to see through blurry vision, but his hair didn’t look like a deeper red than usual. The blood was imperceptible to my eyes…perhaps I didn’t want to see it. My brain must be imagining the rise and fall of his chest; that, or he was slipping away right now.

“I’m sorry,” I whispered. “You w-were the best friend I ever had. I failed you. I always f-failed you, and I…MARCEL! D-don’t leave me!”

Why did my human have to die? Why?!

My emotions devolved into an incoherent whirlwind, and I released a visceral wail. I slammed my good arm into his gut, furious at the universe. A high-pitched yelp came from beneath me, and Marcel’s corpse shifted. My vision refocused on him, watching as he moved an arm to his head. The human’s eyelids fluttered, and a grimace crossed his face.

My best friend pinched his nose. “Oh God…that rung my bell.”

The grief that was fueling me dissipated. I clung to his warm chest with sobs of relief, and Dino came over to lick his face. Marcel pushed the dog away, an instinctive snarl on his lips. He unclipped his helmet, inspecting it with amazement. I gasped at the nick in the cloth lining; the bullet had grazed my human on the dome.

The red-haired soldier hoisted himself up, clutching me to his chest. I felt his wonderful fingers fiddling with my ears, and mewled my adoration. Alarm coursed through my veins, as Marcel stumbled. His skull absorbed much of the impact; the Terran might well be concussed. But he was blissfully alive, and that was music to my ears.

“I love you, Marc, the same as I did my flesh-and-blood brother. I care about you so much,” I whispered in a faint voice. “I know I disappointed you. But you…you never disappointed me.”

His hazel eyes moistened. “What did I tell you? I got the best Venlil. I’m only disappointed in how you view the world.”

It took Marcel an agonizing minute to retrace his steps, and arrive at our impromptu base. The predator sank against a wall, and leaned his head back. He allowed me to burrow into his stomach, snarling through his exhaustion. Virnt was giddy at the “humma’s return”, though his mother kept him at a distance.

Marcel peeked at my arm, and his mental fog vanished. He snapped at Birla, livid that she hadn’t tended to my wounds. The Tilfish general cowered at his ferocity, but I could tell he was just rattled. My human knew how close he came to dying; it didn’t help his mindset to reckon with my critical condition.

The human cleared his throat. “This might hurt, okay? Everything is going to be alright, Slanek. I’m not going anywhere.”

“Please forgive me. There’s nothing I w-wouldn’t do for you.” I wrapped my tail around Marcel’s wrist, and tensed up as he stitched my wound. “I…I don’t want to leave any…bad blood between us.”

“You hurt my feelings, that’s all. Virnt should be institutionalized for liking me? I’m that terrible to my best friend?”

“It’s…n-not like—OW! I l-like you. But t-things about you…should trigger fear at first.”

“Why? You know the Federation lied to you. They lied about us, omnivores like the Tilfish, and basic biology. I’m telling you it was all lies: predator disease and ‘feral’ predators are their ideas too. Stop regurgitating them.”

“T-there are people with predator disease. They…hurt people.”

“But predator disease isn’t just assigned to violent sociopaths. It’s used on anyone who’s wired differently. Do you realize by the Federation’s definition, you have predator disease?”

“No. That’s c-crazy, Marc.”

“I know. I fucking know! Mental health is a complicated thing, with thousands of conditions with unique attributes. Not all of them are violent. Not all of them need to be erased.”

Marcel finished patching me up, and retrieved a radio from his supplies. I mulled over his words, though my brainpower was running on empty. If predator disease was another vessel for Federation lies, that meant we were locking away harmless people. No wonder my human was upset with my suggestion for Virnt. It was the same as how Doctor Zarn wanted to “treat” me for defending Marcel.

So there are different types of predator disease, with different causes and manifestations. And they…we use fear to ostracize every patient.

“I’m sorry,” I croaked.

Marcel squeezed my paw. “I’m sorry too. I should’ve talked to you about these things sooner. It’s my responsibility to educate you, but I’ve just tried to shield you.”

“I know I’m not easy to talk to. I…I know it hurts you when I freak out…or misinterpret you. You know, I wanted to kill Dino earlier…and I almost did.”

“None of that matters now. You’ve been my rock, Slanek. You brought me back from the edge, and you made me believe there was good in the galaxy.”

“T-that’s all I could ever want. Hey, if anything happens to me, tell my parents what w—”

“Tell them yourself. We’re getting out of here. I’m going to call for help, and try to make contact with the UN. Sounds good, huh?”

I didn’t have the heart to tell him the United Nations was long gone. Just as they hadn’t come back for the soldiers on the cradle, nobody was swooping down to the sewers to rescue us. General Birla seemed unconvinced as well; the evacuation announcement stated the deadline in no uncertain terms. At least I could share my last hours with Marcel, rather than dying alone.

My human switched on his radio. “UN fleet, do you copy? This is Captain Marcel Fraser; we have a Venlil VIP in need of medevac. Transmitting our coordinates, over.”

There was no response once Marcel finished his message. The static didn’t seem to deter his efforts, since he repeated his transmission several times. I nuzzled against his wrist, and felt my eyelids becoming heavy. The predator’s warmth helped with my dropping temperature.

“Don’t worry. I’ll keep calling them,” Marcel growled. “When they beat back the Arxur, they’ll come.”

I closed my eyes. “Yeah. Humans will win.”

“We sure will. Sleep well, Slanek.”

Dino sidled up to me as I dozed off, and my instincts rekindled. He placed his coarse snout on my leg, and my mind circled back to Federation lies. The dog hadn’t shown any signs of being evil; he seemed loyal to the humans through thick and thin. Maybe Marcel was right about giving him a chance too.

Predators couldn’t be inherently monstrous when the Terrans existed. This was a simple choice about whether the Federation defined the Venlil. I pressed one paw atop the dog’s back, trusting my human to protect me. Marcel wouldn’t put me in danger, and he said Dino was a friend.

The safest place in this Arxur raid was sandwiched between two watchful predators. Knowing this slumber might be my last, I drifted off at peace with my fate.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯